Just a reminder, this is what our final exercise looks like, we can select different languages
here and then go and hit the GitHub search API and display the results.
Pretty straightforward, flask app, there's no, we're not using a database here, we're
not really maintaining any state, we're just checking what the user checked and unchecked
the feature request.
Pretty easy peasy.
Now let's go through how to implement this.
I'm going to exit out of the development server that I was using and I'm going to run
a command to call tree that's going to list the directory structure for this chapter.
If you're on Mac OS, just know that this utility doesn't come with Mac, you have to install
it.
So at the root, we have API.py, I have exceptions.py, where I put my custom exception.
I have models.py, where I put the model that stores my GitHub repository.
Then I have a static folder with a faevacon from my website, CSS styles that I've provided
for you.
Please don't get the pitchforks out if my CSS isn't good, I'm one of those full stack developers.
But then we have a few templates.
We have a template for an error page and a template for our index page, as well as some tests
that we can run.
Let's go through and look at these files.
Our exception.py file is pretty straightforward.
I have a class here and like you saw before it, inherits from exception.
In the constructor, I'm taking a status code.
If the status code was for a three, it's going to say rate limit reached.
If the status code was any other type of error status code, it's going to print that out.
Then I pass this new modified message that I created to a super dot in it.
Looking at the model's file, we live coded this earlier.
This class, the GitHub repo class, is used to represent a single GitHub repository.
In my constructor, I take the name, the language, the number of stars.
I also return a handy string representation and a wrapper.
Now looking at API.py.
This is where I put my create query and my repos with most stars methods.
Remember that we were methods that look almost exactly like this in the intro to Python final exercise.
Going through these for creating a query, I take a list of languages and the minimum amount of stars.
In yesterday's code, we were looping over each query adding it on to the string,
using concatenate, using the string join is much more efficient.
Concatenate is a string concatenation is a pretty inefficient operation and using string join as much faster.
Now we can make that same query using an F string for language, going through each language and languages,
stripping out any trailing or leading white space, and then creating our new query with just one concatenation and concatenating the minimum number of stars that we'd like to see.
Now in the re-boes with most stars method, we get our query by using that query method.
We have the same parameters, I've printed them out here, but you don't need to do that in your code.
I get the response by using the request library to get the resource at this GitHub API search URL, passing in the parameters I set up.
Now if the status code was not 200, that means if anything went wrong, I'm just going to raise instance of my GitHub API exception,
passing in the response.status code.
Next, I get the JSON from the response, I get the items at the items key, and I'm just going to use a list comprehension to return an instance of my GitHub repo.
A list of instances of my GitHub repo class, passing in the name, the language, and the Stargazers count, and using a list comprehension to do that for each item in items.
Notice there is no main method here, we're not running our code in the same file, instead we're going to be using this as a library from our Flask app.
We're scrolling to the top, notice that we imported requests so that we can use it as an available library.
We're also importing a few things from our own custom classes, so our GitHub API exception and our GitHub repo model.
Those are all the building blocks.
Now open app.py, and see how it all gets put together.
For you Windows folks, I'm going to, I'm going to put in additional instructions here to see who have them in one place with the final exercise.
But we have a few imports here as well, we're importing a few things from Flask where importing the Flask class, we're importing render template.
And we're also importing something called request, which gives us information about the request that we are currently processing.
For my API, I'm also importing this repo with most stars, method, and I'm importing my GitHub API exception, so that I can catch it, do something with it.
I'm creating a new app, a new Flask app here by passing in a Dundername, and then a making a list of available languages that I want my users of my web application to be able to choose from.
And I have a index method here.
If you've noticed here at the top, my app.row takes a list of methods that it accepts.
So if I try to call this route with a method that is not accepted, like put, my server is just going to throw an error.
Now, if the requested method was get, meaning we haven't submitted anything yet, we're not hitting that submit button.
I'm just going to set the selected languages to all of the available languages by default.
If the method was post-instead, I'm going to use that request variable that I imported from Flask.
That variable has a form, which is attached to the form that I've used to submit to this endpoint.
And there's a helper method on this called get list.
And this tells me which form I would like to look at.
Now, I get my results from the repos with most stars method, just like I did in my introduction to Python final exercise.
This time, instead of passing in all of the languages, I'm just going to pass in the ones that the user selected.
Next, I'm going to render my template.
So the first argument to render template is index.hgml.
We'll take a look at that template in just a second.
I'm also passing in which languages were selected, so that when the page reloads, the languages that we had checked off stay checked off.
And I'm passing in that list of all of the available languages, so that the checkboxes know whether they're selected or not.
And to display the check on or off, I'm lastly, I'm just passing in one additional variable to the template.
And that's our list of results, which contain those instances of get her repo.
There's one last thing that happens down here.
I'm using another decorator.
This one is called app.ir handler.
And to this decorator, I can pass an exception type.
And just provide a single method that will run if this class of exception occurs.
And here, I'm going to render a different type of template, error.hgml.
And the message is just going to be the string representation of the error.
Let's take a look at what's in these templates.
First, I'm going to open error.hgml from my final exercise files, and we'll see that I link to a
style sheet. I have a div here, but really the most important bit is I'm just going to display the message
that got passed in one second. Let me close some of these files.
And I'm going to open my app.py. Oops, that's not what I wanted. Sorry, one second.
App.py is right here. And I'm going to open my error.hml file.
Okay, let me see if I can display these side by side with my current font size.
Okay, so here I'm returning render template. I'm passing in the message, which is the
exception that was thrown. And here in my template, I'm looking at that message, and with these curly
braces printing it out. Okay, now I'm going to open index.hgml from the final exercise template
directory. And we'll see I have a title here, but the the body is pretty strong. The body of
this is pretty short, pretty easy to read. So here are the form action that I'm taking. I'm using
this built in that's available in templates. And I'm asking for the index the URL for this index
method that I've created right here. So I don't have to do any weird things with paths. And I'm
specifying in my form that the method is post. Now you'll remember that here in my index method,
I'm rendering a template and I'm passing in a few things to this template. The selected
languages, the available languages, and the results. So I'm going to loop through each language in my
available languages. And I'm going to do, I'm going to set the value to the language for that checkbox
so that when I submit this form, I have that language available to me. And then I'm going to return
checked. I'm going to insert here checked if the language is in the selected languages. Otherwise,
the checkbox is going to be unchecked. And finally, I'm going to print out the label for the language.
That generates this section right here. Lastly, I just have a submit button. Remember that for
junta templates, I'm going to have to end this four statement, because just like each
channel, there's that opening tag and a closing tag. Now I'm going to print out my popular
get her proposed by stars. And all I'm doing here, again, I passed in results to my template.
If there are no results, I don't want to bother rendering the table. It's going to look ugly.
So instead, I'm just going to print out no results. Otherwise, I'm going to print out the
table header. Now, I'm going to loop through every result in my results. And for table data,
I'll pull the result name, result language, and results. num stars. And that's it. This is a
60 line index.hml file. And that's all that we need to generate this functional website.
This is the kind of project that you can easily do in an afternoon. One more thing I want to
to show you, I wrote a few simple unit tests for my application. I also wrote a few unit tests
for the simple application. Those tests are included in the repo. So if you'd like,
take a look at those and run them, and let's make sure our app works.